# Kamal Pangeni, Ph.D.

+1 (801) 921-2420 • kamalpangeni@gmail.com • github.com/kamalpangeni www.linkedin.com/in/kamalpangeni • scholar.google.com/+KamalPangeniPhD

#### **Professional Profile**

Trained as a theoretical high energy physicist, I enjoy solving complex problems with innovative ideas. My background in physics provides a solid foundation for quantitative problem solving skills. I have extensive experience in data manipulation, data analysis, building machine learning models, and deploying the product to end users at a large organization.

# **Areas of Expertise**

- Supervised and Unsupervised Machine Learning
- Natural Language Processing
- Mathematical modeling
- Monte Carlo modeling and simulations

- Deep Learning
- Statistical analysis
- Algorithm development and implementation
- Problem solving

## **Skills**

Computer Languages: Python, Mathematica, SQL, MATLAB, C++, java, LATEX

Data analysis and visualization: Numpy, Pandas, Matplotlib, Seaborn, QlikView, QlikSense

Machine Learning: Scikit-Learn, Keras, XGboost, LightGBM, Tensorflow, Pytorch

AutoML: H20.ai, DataRobot

Languages: English, Nepali, Hindi, Urdu

# **Experience**

## Data Scientist - Machine Learning @Mercy Hospital, St. Louis

Feb 2018-Present

I develop machine learning models to drive operational efficiency and create profitability.

- Built and deployed machine learning models to predict the Diagnosis Related Group (DRG) for inpatient admissions. Within a year of its deployment, it has already saved more than 7 million dollars in hospital revenue. This project was selected as a finalist (in cost and efficiency category) at Mercy wide innovation conference.
- Developed Qlik Sense app to share the predictions from the model with medical coders who are currently using it to audit and review medical coding at Mercy.
- Built a Natural Language Processing model based on deep learning to predict the diagnosis for inpatient admission from physician notes.
- Estimated the financial impact of elective surgery cancellations due to COVID19.
- Used Natural Language Processing techniques to automate the cancer registry case findings.

#### **Graduate Research Assistant**

#### @Washington University, St. Louis

Aug 2013-Aug 2017

I worked on several aspects of quantum chromodynamics (QCD) at nonzero temperature and density. My principle achievements included:

- Development and implementation of algorithms to find the saddle point of a multi-dimensional function, and perform multi-dimensional integration numerically, as required to study the phase structure of QCD and liquid-gas system.
- Computation of the mass spectrum and correlation functions in lattice models of QCD by numerically diagonalizing matrices of large dimensions.
- Perform multi-dimensional integral numerically using Monte Carlo techniques to calculate the rate of neutrino emission from neutron stars.

#### Undergraduate Research Assistant @Brigham Young University

May 2008-Aug 2011

- I successfully constructed and tested a time-of-flight ion spectrometer that was later used in single photon radiation experiment. As part of the testing of the apparatus, I collected a large set of data from experiments and performed data analysis (primarily Mathematica).
- In making a brief transition to algebraic topology, I quickly learned new ideas and applied it to my research. My main focus was to identify different triangulations and circle packing on the surface of a sphere and use it to investigate the properties of knots with less than nine twist regions.

# Kamal Pangeni, Ph.D.

+1 (801) 921-2420 • kamalpangeni@wustl.edu • github.com/kamalpangeni www.linkedin.com/in/kamalpangeni • scholar.google.com/+KamalPangeniPhD

### **Education**

Washington University	St. Louis MO
Doctor of Philosophy in Physics 3.89/4	Aug 2017
Dissertation: Topics in QCD at nonzero temperature and density	
Masters of Science in Physics 3.79/4	May 2013
Brigham Young University	Provo,UT
Bachelors of Science in Physics and Mathematics 3.7/4	Jan 2007-Aug 2011

# **Machine Learning Courses on Coursera**

Reinforcement Learning Specialization (4 courses)	March 2020
Introduction to TensorFlow for AI, ML and DL	June 2019
Deep Learning Specialization (5 Courses)	May 2019
How to Win a Data Science Competition	June 2018
Machine Learning	Nov 2017

## **Honors and Awards**

• Finalist in Mercy wide innovation conference	Oct 2019
• Winner of 1st Mercy Hackathon [link]	Sept 2019
• Arthur L. Hughes Fellow, Washington University[link]	Summer 2012
• University Fellow, Washington University [link]	2011 & 2013
• Harvery Fletcher Scholarship, Brigham Young University	2010/2011
• Academic Scholarship, Brigham Young University	2007-2010
• Physics Department Scholarship, Brigham Young University	2007-2010

### **Publications**

(Note: In high energy physics, name of authors are listed in alphabetical order)

- M. Alford, **K. Pangeni** and A. Windisch "Color Superconductivity and Charge Neutrality in Yukawa Theory", Physics Review Letters 120, 082701 (2018)
- H. Nishimura, M. Ogilvie and **K. Pangeni**, "Liquid-Gas Phase Transition and *CK* Symmetry in Quantum Field Theories", Physical Review D 95, 076003(2017).
- Mark Alford and **Kamal Pangeni** "Gap bridging enhancement of modified Urca process in nuclear matter.", Physical Review C 95, 015802 (2017).
- H. Nishimura, M. Ogilvie and **K. Pangeni**, "Complex mass spectrum in lattice QCD with static quarks at strong coupling", Physical Review D 93, 094501 (2016).
- H. Nishimura, M. Ogilvie and **K. Pangeni**, "Complex saddle points and disorder lines in QCD at finite temperature and density", Physical Review D 91,054004 (2015).
- H. Nishimura, M. Ogilvie and **K. Pangeni**, "Complex saddle points in QCD at finite temperature and density", Physical Review D 90,045039 (2014).